<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-US"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.5.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en-US" /><updated>2018-01-09T11:42:56-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Kamran Haider</title><subtitle>Ensemble of Thoughts</subtitle><author><name>Kamran Haider</name></author><entry><title type="html">Modeling Proton Hopping</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/projects/2017/12/28/proton-hopping.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modeling Proton Hopping" /><published>2017-12-28T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/projects/2017/12/28/proton-hopping</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/projects/2017/12/28/proton-hopping.html">&lt;p&gt;If not for proton-hopping, we wouldn’t be alive. Indeed, a crucial step in aerobic respiration is the proton-coupled
electron transport at the mitochondrial membrane. The proteins that facilitate this process take up protons from the 
surroundings and move them across membranes. The study of proton diffusion in aqueous media and across proteins is a 
major area of research in biochemistry and molecular biophysics and also a focus of research at 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sci.ccny.cuny.edu/~gunner/&quot;&gt;Gunner Lab&lt;/a&gt;, where I work. My main project here is to calculate energetics of 
proton-hopping in relatively simple systems (such as Gramicidin channel) and in proteins such as Cytochrome c Oxidase (CcO). 
The main tool in my kit is the Multi-conformer Continuum Electrostatics (MCCE) approach, which is essentially a 
Monte Carlo simulation method to model protontation state changes in biomolecules. We wish to develop an extension of 
MCCE to evaluate proton transfer paths in membrane spanning proteins like CcO to develop a complete picture of how 
protons move from one side of the membrane to the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am in the process of organizing the data and code from this project into a robust and reproducible workflow. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kamran-haider/ProtonHopping&quot;&gt;project repository&lt;/a&gt; is up but is being updated frequently. The notebooks subdirectory will contain key results and analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kamran Haider</name></author><category term="projects" /><summary type="html">If not for proton-hopping, we wouldn’t be alive. Indeed, a crucial step in aerobic respiration is the proton-coupled electron transport at the mitochondrial membrane. The proteins that facilitate this process take up protons from the surroundings and move them across membranes. The study of proton diffusion in aqueous media and across proteins is a major area of research in biochemistry and molecular biophysics and also a focus of research at Gunner Lab, where I work. My main project here is to calculate energetics of proton-hopping in relatively simple systems (such as Gramicidin channel) and in proteins such as Cytochrome c Oxidase (CcO). The main tool in my kit is the Multi-conformer Continuum Electrostatics (MCCE) approach, which is essentially a Monte Carlo simulation method to model protontation state changes in biomolecules. We wish to develop an extension of MCCE to evaluate proton transfer paths in membrane spanning proteins like CcO to develop a complete picture of how protons move from one side of the membrane to the other.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Machine Learning for Predicting Blood Brain Barrier Crossing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/projects/2017/12/27/bbbp-ml.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Machine Learning for Predicting Blood Brain Barrier Crossing" /><published>2017-12-27T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/projects/2017/12/27/bbbp-ml</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/projects/2017/12/27/bbbp-ml.html">&lt;p&gt;I recently started working on an independent machine learning project, partly inspired by the idea
that understanding machine learning requires having a problem to work on. The development of drugs that target central 
nervous system requires crossing the blood-brain barrier, a natural mechanism for the brain to prevent
chemicals with certain properties from barging in. In a drug discovery campaign for a CNS traget, it is worthwhile knowing 
eraly on if the promising compounds can cross this barrier. 
That’s where machine-learning can come in handy. My current goals are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1/ Reproduce &lt;a href=&quot;http://http://moleculenet.ai/&quot;&gt;MoleculeNet&lt;/a&gt; benchmarks for the performance of a diverse set of machine learning algorithms on the 
Blood-brain barrier prediction &lt;a href=&quot;http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/ci300124c&quot;&gt;dataset&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2/ Diagnose issues leading to poor model performance on test data and develop strategies to improve performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the long term, I am also interested in evaluating if deep learning neural networks can give a significant performance boost. 
The best place to see current progress is to directly go to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kamran-haider/bbbp_ml_study/tree/master/notes&quot;&gt;notes&lt;/a&gt; 
or &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kamran-haider/bbbp_ml_study/tree/master/scratch&quot;&gt;scratch&lt;/a&gt; subdirecties of the project 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kamran-haider/bbbp_ml_study&quot;&gt;Github repository&lt;/a&gt;. From time to time, I will post about the ongoing 
progress and results on the &lt;a href=&quot;/home&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kamran Haider</name></author><category term="projects" /><summary type="html">I recently started working on an independent machine learning project, partly inspired by the idea that understanding machine learning requires having a problem to work on. The development of drugs that target central nervous system requires crossing the blood-brain barrier, a natural mechanism for the brain to prevent chemicals with certain properties from barging in. In a drug discovery campaign for a CNS traget, it is worthwhile knowing eraly on if the promising compounds can cross this barrier. That’s where machine-learning can come in handy. My current goals are:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Developing and Maintaining SSTMap</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/projects/2017/12/27/SSTMap.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Developing and Maintaining SSTMap" /><published>2017-12-27T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/projects/2017/12/27/SSTMap</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/projects/2017/12/27/SSTMap.html">&lt;p&gt;I continue developing and maintaining SSTMap, which is my first complete software project. 
SSTMap is a valuable addition to an expanding set of software packages for the analysis of water molecules in 
molecular dynamics trajectories. Its main advantages are its applicability across multiple MD platforms and flexibility in
carrying out calculations in different forms (e.g., grid-based vs cluster-based, choosing all or a subset of energy, entropy
and hydrogen bonding calculations). There is still plenty of room for improvement in its API and efficiency, 
which I am working on. Stay tuned for more updates on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://sstmap.org&quot;&gt;project website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kamran Haider</name></author><category term="projects" /><summary type="html">I continue developing and maintaining SSTMap, which is my first complete software project. SSTMap is a valuable addition to an expanding set of software packages for the analysis of water molecules in molecular dynamics trajectories. Its main advantages are its applicability across multiple MD platforms and flexibility in carrying out calculations in different forms (e.g., grid-based vs cluster-based, choosing all or a subset of energy, entropy and hydrogen bonding calculations). There is still plenty of room for improvement in its API and efficiency, which I am working on. Stay tuned for more updates on the project website</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">IsingPy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/projects/2017/12/26/isingpy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="IsingPy" /><published>2017-12-26T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/projects/2017/12/26/isingpy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/projects/2017/12/26/isingpy.html">&lt;p&gt;IsingPy began as a fun project to use the famous Ising model to learn and implement statistical physics algrithms.
My goals in this project are twofold:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1\ Develop efficient implementations of Monte Carlo algorithms to sample spin states and calculate macroscopic observables, such as magnetization and average energy. This is more of a textbook style approach in learning statsitcal physics with Ising model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2\ In a more ambitious attempt at a later stage, I wish to explore the crossover of statistical physics and machine learning
using Ising model, e.g., building generative models that sample spin states, using deep learning to solve inverse ising inference problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, I have managed to write the basic &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kamran-haider/isingpy/blob/master/examples/modeling_ising_magnets_first_attempt.ipynb&quot;&gt;code&lt;/a&gt; 
that simulates Ising models of moderate sizes and reproduces the phase 
transition at the critical temperature. Currently, I am working to implement more advanced approaches, 
such as cluster algorithms, as outlined in Chapter 5 of 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://global.oup.com/academic/product/statistical-mechanics-9780198515364?cc=us&amp;amp;lang=en&amp;amp;&quot;&gt;Statistical Mechanics Algorithms and Computations&lt;/a&gt; 
by Werner Krauth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For goal 2, I am waiting to go through the convolutional neural networks course on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/specializations/deep-learning&quot;&gt;Coursera Deep Learning Specialization&lt;/a&gt;, 
which I have signed up for. I am hoping that this course will equip me with tools to build and train appropriate deep learning
models for Ising systems to solve problems such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/nphys4035&quot;&gt;learning phase transitions&lt;/a&gt; 
and &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1706.08466&quot;&gt;inverse Ising inference&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kamran Haider</name></author><category term="projects" /><summary type="html">IsingPy began as a fun project to use the famous Ising model to learn and implement statistical physics algrithms. My goals in this project are twofold:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Solvation Structure and Thermodynamic Mapping</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/papers/2017/11/21/SSTMap.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Solvation Structure and Thermodynamic Mapping" /><published>2017-11-21T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-11-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/papers/2017/11/21/SSTMap</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/papers/2017/11/21/SSTMap.html">&lt;p&gt;We describe the implementation and features of &lt;a href=&quot;http://sstmap.org&quot;&gt;SSTMap&lt;/a&gt;, an interoperable package for the analysis of water molecules in molecualr dynamics simulations of biomolecules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Haider K&lt;/strong&gt;, Cruz A, Ramsey S, Gilson M. and Kurtzman T. Solvation Structure and Thermodynamic Mapping (SSTMap): An Open-Source, Flexible Package for the Analysis of Water in Molecular Dynamics Trajectories. &lt;a href=&quot;http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/acs.jctc.7b00592&quot;&gt;J. Chem. Theory Comput. 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kamran Haider</name></author><category term="papers" /><summary type="html">We describe the implementation and features of SSTMap, an interoperable package for the analysis of water molecules in molecualr dynamics simulations of biomolecules.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22thumb%22=%3E%22sstmap.png%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Predicting Host-Guest Binding in the SAMPL5 Challenge</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/papers/2016/09/30/AGBNP2-HSA.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Predicting Host-Guest Binding in the SAMPL5 Challenge" /><published>2016-09-30T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-09-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/papers/2016/09/30/AGBNP2-HSA</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/papers/2016/09/30/AGBNP2-HSA.html">&lt;p&gt;As part of a collaboration between &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lehman.edu/faculty/tkurtzman/&quot;&gt;Kurtzman Lab&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ronlevygroup.cst.temple.edu/&quot;&gt;Levy Group&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.compmolbiophysbc.org/&quot;&gt;Gallicheo Lab&lt;/a&gt;, we headed to SAMPL5-blinded challenge for predicting host-guest binding affinities. This work employed BEDAM absolute free energy calculations with an implicit solvent model parameterized by IFST-based hydration site analysis. After inclduing a Debye–Hückel treatment of salt effects, calculations were in good agreemnt with the experimental results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pal R K, &lt;strong&gt;Haider K&lt;/strong&gt;, Kaur D, Flynn W, Xia J, Levy R M, Taran T, Wickstrom L, Kurtzman T, Gallicchio E. A combined treatment of hydration and dynamical effects for the modeling of host–guest binding thermodynamics: the SAMPL5 blinded challenge. &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10822-016-9956-6&quot;&gt;JCAMD. 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kamran Haider</name></author><category term="papers" /><summary type="html">As part of a collaboration between Kurtzman Lab, Levy Group and Gallicheo Lab, we headed to SAMPL5-blinded challenge for predicting host-guest binding affinities. This work employed BEDAM absolute free energy calculations with an implicit solvent model parameterized by IFST-based hydration site analysis. After inclduing a Debye–Hückel treatment of salt effects, calculations were in good agreemnt with the experimental results.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22thumb%22=%3E%22sampl5-study.png%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Enthalpic Breakdown of Water Structure</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/papers/2016/05/11/Enthalpic-Breakdown.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Enthalpic Breakdown of Water Structure" /><published>2016-05-11T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-05-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/papers/2016/05/11/Enthalpic-Breakdown</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/papers/2016/05/11/Enthalpic-Breakdown.html">&lt;p&gt;In this study, we used simple measures of water structure to characterize active-site solvation using hydration site analysis. We gained valuable insights into the behavior of water under constrined surface topographies of protein active-sites and noted that structural measures, alongside solvation thermodynamics, can be useful in evaluating water displacement for ligand optimization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Haider K&lt;/strong&gt;, Wickstrom L, Ramsey S, Gilson M, Kurtzman T. Enthalpic breakdown of water structure on protein active-site surfaces. &lt;a href=&quot;http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/acs.jpcb.6b01094&quot;&gt;J.
Phys. Chem.B. 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kamran Haider</name></author><category term="papers" /><summary type="html">In this study, we used simple measures of water structure to characterize active-site solvation using hydration site analysis. We gained valuable insights into the behavior of water under constrined surface topographies of protein active-sites and noted that structural measures, alongside solvation thermodynamics, can be useful in evaluating water displacement for ligand optimization.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22thumb%22=%3E%22water-breakdown.png%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Solvation Analysis and Functional Group Mapping of Protein Active-Sites</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/papers/2013/09/26/MCSS-IFST.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Solvation Analysis and Functional Group Mapping of Protein Active-Sites" /><published>2013-09-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2013-09-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/papers/2013/09/26/MCSS-IFST</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/papers/2013/09/26/MCSS-IFST.html">&lt;p&gt;Predicting displacement of water molecules from a target active-site is a worthwhile but challenging endevor. Here, we combined inhomogeneous solvation theory (IFST) with MCSS to predict water displacement from the HSP90 active-site. While IFST alone performed better than the combined approach in predicting water displacement, the MCSS provided valuable insight into functional groups suitable for displacing the waters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Haider K&lt;/strong&gt;, Huggins DJ. Combining Solvent Thermodynamic Profiles with Functionality Maps of the Hsp90 Binding Site to Predict
the Displacement of Water Molecules. &lt;a href=&quot;http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/ci4003409&quot;&gt;J. Chem. Inf. Model. 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kamran Haider</name></author><category term="papers" /><summary type="html">Predicting displacement of water molecules from a target active-site is a worthwhile but challenging endevor. Here, we combined inhomogeneous solvation theory (IFST) with MCSS to predict water displacement from the HSP90 active-site. While IFST alone performed better than the combined approach in predicting water displacement, the MCSS provided valuable insight into functional groups suitable for displacing the waters.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22thumb%22=%3E%22mcss-ifts.png%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Modeling Resistance Mutations in Hepatitis C Virus NS3 Protease</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/papers/2013/01/24/NS3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modeling Resistance Mutations in Hepatitis C Virus NS3 Protease" /><published>2013-01-24T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2013-01-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/papers/2013/01/24/NS3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/papers/2013/01/24/NS3.html">&lt;p&gt;As local HCV patients in Pakistan became increasingly affected by antiviral drug resistance, we set out to model the active-site mutations of NS3 protease, a key anti-HCV drug target. Using impicit-solvent binding energy calculations, we developed a protocol for resistance-profiling of promising clinical candidates. While modeling studies helped us understand the mechanism of resistance, the predictive ability of the approach was hampered potentially by binding-induced structural rearrangments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hotiana HA, &lt;strong&gt;Haider K&lt;/strong&gt;. Structural Modeling of HCV NS3/4A Serine Protease Drug-Resistance Mutations Using End-Point Continuum
Solvation and Side-Chain Flexibility Calculations. &lt;a href=&quot;http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/ci3004754&quot;&gt;J. Chem. Inf. Model. 2013.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kamran Haider</name></author><category term="papers" /><summary type="html">As local HCV patients in Pakistan became increasingly affected by antiviral drug resistance, we set out to model the active-site mutations of NS3 protease, a key anti-HCV drug target. Using impicit-solvent binding energy calculations, we developed a protocol for resistance-profiling of promising clinical candidates. While modeling studies helped us understand the mechanism of resistance, the predictive ability of the approach was hampered potentially by binding-induced structural rearrangments.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22thumb%22=%3E%22ns3.png%22%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Multi-copy Simultaneous Search (MCSS) Method for Docking</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/papers/2011/04/29/MCSS-GBSA.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Multi-copy Simultaneous Search (MCSS) Method for Docking" /><published>2011-04-29T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2011-04-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/papers/2011/04/29/MCSS-GBSA</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/papers/2011/04/29/MCSS-GBSA.html">&lt;p&gt;Inspired by the progress in fragment-based drug discovery, we resurrected MCSS, an approach for functional group mapping of protin active-sites developed in early 1990s. We modified it by including energetic terms from implicit solvent energy calculations and tested its performance in predicting binding and ranking ordering of fragments to HSP90.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Haider K&lt;/strong&gt;, Bertrand HO, Hubbard RE. Predicting Fragment Binding Poses Using a Combined MCSS MM-GBSA Approach. &lt;a href=&quot;http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/ci100469n&quot;&gt;J. Chem. Inf.
Model. 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kamran Haider</name></author><category term="papers" /><summary type="html">Inspired by the progress in fragment-based drug discovery, we resurrected MCSS, an approach for functional group mapping of protin active-sites developed in early 1990s. We modified it by including energetic terms from implicit solvent energy calculations and tested its performance in predicting binding and ranking ordering of fragments to HSP90.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22thumb%22=%3E%22mcss-icon.jpeg%22%7D" /></entry></feed>